A Guide to the Papers of Alexander H. H. Stuart and the related Stuart and Baldwin families
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Horace H. Day discusses the charges brought against the Commissioner of Patents, Mr. Thomas Ewbanks (1792-1870) saying his official conduct has been one-sided, partial, and not in accordance with the rules and laws of the Patent Office (1851 Feb 7) and asking if the New York papers have correctly reported Alexander H. H. Stuart 's comments about the charges (1851 Mar 12)
Wills De Hass (1818?-1910) sends a copy of his History of Western Virginia (1851 Jul 24); wants Alexander H. H. Stuart to be a candidate for Vice-President (1851 Oct 6); voices concerns over his application for a consulship or another office (1852 Jun 1 & Oct 18); two letters furnish private details of the Baltimore Convention (1852 Jun 20); and hopes for a position in the Maryland Historical Society (1853 Feb 16)
William D. Delany tries to enlist Stuart's aid in securing the office of Inspector of the Custom House at Norfolk (1851 Nov 25) or the Postmaster office at Norfolk (1852 Sep 29)
Charles Devens, Jr., U.S. Marshal, Boston, letter introducing General John S. Tyler (1852 May 24)
Samuel Dickson writes concerning the Patrick Brady v Daniel C.E. Brady suit for $ 50,000 growing out of the dissolving of a partnership in 1857; and describes the Bath Iron Works and Buffalo Forge property (1867 Apr 24)
D[orothea] L[ynde] Dix (1802-1887) writes six letters to Alexander H. H. Stuart concerning the establishment of a first class hospital in Washington, D.C. and seeks the aid of Captain Randolph in the Legislature of [Virginia ?] ([ca. 1851-1853])
James B. Dorman writes that the Whigs of Rockbridge unanimously desire the nomination of Millard Fillmore as President; believes the hostility to Fillmore stems from his approval of the Compromise of 1850 and his "fidelity to the Constitutional rights of the South"; and many Whigs object strongly to General Winfield Scott 's Roman Catholic affinities (1852 Jun 7)
John Doyle writes that he has recommended Alexander H. H. Stuart to the prominent Whigs in Pennsylvania as the best choice for nomination to the Vice-Presidency while he favors Fillmore for the Presidency over Scott (1851 Sep 20); his concern over the imminent split in the Whig Party of Lexington, Virginia (1852 Dec 4); his son, R.L. Doyle, writes concerning their Alum Springs property containing iron deposits and several mineral springs and asks the aid of Alexander H. H. Stuart in securing a loan to convert their property into a viable health resort (1853 Jan 7)
G.G. Dyer defends his change of political parties from Whig to Democratic based on his open support of the Tariff and the United States Bank and extols the virtue of the new state of Iowa which he describes as a land of beauty and opportunity (1851 Sep 27)
J.L. Edwards, Pension Office, discusses the claims of the descendants of Colonel Alexander McClanahan to land based on his Revolutionary War service, with the Committee of Safety for the Colony of Virginia form appointing Alexander McClanahan to Lt. Col. of the 7th Regiment of Regular Forces attached (1776 Feb 29 & 1843 May 19)
Vespasian Ellis discusses the plan of organization adopted at the National Council where a Committee of 13 was appointed to take the general charge of the interests of the American Party which was presented to the Council by himself; the plan was adopted unanimously but the Chairman E. Brooks received the credit for the plan; he suggested that Alexander H. H. Stuart would be a good person from Virginia to be on the Central Committee of 13; mentions the efforts of Baldwin of Connecticut and others to "free soilize" the party platform and the fact that he opposed and defeated the plan was suppressed in the report on the proceedings in the Louisville Journal (1857 Jun 10)
Erie Railroad Company Board of Directors offers to Alexander H. H. Stuart free use of the railroad as member of the Cabinet (1851 Jul 12)
Edward Everett (1794-1865), Secretary of State, regrets he will not be able to dine with Alexander H. H. Stuart due to personal illness (1852 Dec 20); and informs Alexander H. H. Stuart that General Franklin Pierce wishes for him to continue to act as Secretary of the Interior until his successor is appointed (1853 Feb 26)
Charles James Faulkner (1806-1884) thanks him for his interest in James E. Stewart (1852 Aug 25)
Millard Fillmore letters to Alexander H. H. Stuart -address the question of his feelings toward the South, "I disclaim most unequivocally now and forever any desire on my part to interfere with the rights on what is termed the property of citizens of other states" and encloses a copy of the leading [Lewis] Cass paper in the state showing that Fillmore was denounced at the recent anti-slavery convention at Worcester along with Cass and Taylor (1848 Jul 5); excuses Alexander H. H. Stuart from the Cabinet meeting due to the death of Judge Baldwin (1852 May 19); authorizes Alexander H. H. Stuart to take on the duties of the Secretary of the Navy until his return (1852 Sep 25); thanks him for his letter of condolence upon the death of his wife, Abigail Powers on March 30, 1853 (1853 Jul 11); attempts to make arrangements for a Southern tour in the spring, and says, "This Nebraska matter presents a new phase to things in Washington. But is it wise for the South to set the example repealing the Compromise of 1820 ? If one compromise be disregarded will not another be, and will not the South in the end be left to the tender mercy of Northern fanaticism with an overwhelming numerical majority ?" (1854 Feb 9); observes that with the latest election it appears that the Whig Party has split into two factions, with the abolitionists joining the [Republicans ?] and the rest joining the American Party of Know Nothings and refers to the nomination of Henry Alexander Wise for Governor and his denunciation of the Know Nothings (1854 Dec 14); and informs Alexander H. H. Stuart that Granger will try to meet him in Washington this winter and mentions the efforts of his friends to unite the national elements opposed to the present federal administration into an American Union Party (1854 Dec 22)
Millard Fillmore to Daniel Webster sends John P. Scott over to see Webster concerning a position in the State Department in Londonderry, Ireland, now held by an appointee of President Tyler and says he will go along with whatever Webster wants (1851 Apr 2)
Edward H. Fitzhugh refers to the Bridge case in the Wheeling court (1850 Mar 25) *see newsclippings in Box 2*
E[dmund] Fontaine, Virginia Central Railroad Company, concerning his barley which has been at Waynesboro for some time prior to his letter (1859 Mar 25)
John S. Gallagher discusses the bestowal of advertising patronage by the federal government (1851 Jul 19); the suitability of Shannondale for a military asylum (1851 Aug 4); encloses a letter from William P. Buford, soliciting Alexander H. H. Stuart 's influence to get Mr. Buford's son appointed to a cadetship at West Point (1851 Nov 13); his examination of the controversy about the post office in Winchester and his advice not to remove Milton (1852 Jan 9); encloses letters (not present) from friends desiring positions with the government (1852 Jan 16); introduces Colonel Joseph K. Hartwell (1852 Mar 10); recommends General [James] Singleton for the government position in New Mexico (1852 May 7); and asks for a copy of a letter from the Commissioner of Patents to Dr. James Blake of California (1852 Jul 2).
Robert H. Gallagher, Bank of the Union, Washington asks that part of the Census Fund and the Pension Fund be deposited with him (1851 Dec 9; 1852 Sep 2)
Alexander Galt concerning his position as Postmaster at Norfolk (1851 Jul 31)
J. Garland 's letter of introduction for his relative, Alexander B. Garland (1853 Feb 2)
William H. Garland requests the position of treasurer of the mint at New Orleans (1850 Oct 29) and writes concerning the outrage committed by the authorities of Cuba on the Crescent City [New Orleans ?] (1852 Oct 7)
William Garnett, Collector Custom House, Norfolk, Virginia, concerning the effort being made to remove him from the Custom House (1851 Nov 18 & 1852 Aug 11)
George Washington's Birthday Celebration Committee, Rome, Georgia, requesting Alexander H. H. Stuart 's presence at their celebration and commenting, "The Southern people are terribly oppressed, but are disposed to preserve their manhood untarnished preferring to submit for a while to military despotism rather than to the ruin and degradation of radical rule and negro supremacy" (1868 Feb 11)
R.T. Gibson 's letters are all concerning his futile attempts to secure the position of naval officer at the port of Savannah (1851-1852)
W.M. Gilliam sends Alexander H. H. Stuart 's horse to Washington by Mr. Brent (1852 Mar 15)
T.H. Gilmer seeks more appointments for people from Virginia from the Whig administration (1850 Sep 27)
Thomas W. Gilmer writes that he is sorry that Alexander H. H. Stuart has been involved in controversy, mentions "old [James Iver ?] McKay " as chairman of the Ways & Means Committee, and believes that Texas will come into the Union as fast as it can (1843 Dec 13)
W.W. Gilmer approves Alexander H. H. Stuart 's stand on the National Bank but is not so fond of the election of [Walter ?] Coles (1841 Apr 15)
William L. Goggin (1807-1870) his disappointment over his brother's failure to secure a position, the possibility of getting the postmastership at Sacramento City, and his declaration, "I am a Union man and I have long thought this should be the great issue (irrespective of old party associations) the Union or its Dissolution -God grant it may be perpetual -I repudiate utter fanaticism North or South" (1850 Nov 3); and asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to remove his letter from the files of the War Department requesting an appointment as Visitor to West Point (1852 Mar 10)
G. Goldenberg sends two printed pamphlets (present) entitled Observations Sur La Maladie Des Pommes De Terre in French and a copy in German, presenting his treatise on the Potato Disease (1849 Feb 2)
J.T. Gordon explains being detained in the lieu d'aisance while reading Senator [William McKendree] Gwin 's attack on the Administration (1852 Jul 9)
Willis Arnold Gorman (1816-1876) agrees to a resolution to supply the heads of Departments with copies of the [Presidential Message ?] and accompanying documents (1852 Dec 14)
J. Thompson Graham solicits money for the American Emigrant's Friend Society whose object is to "afford protection from fraud, imposition & extortion to all foreign immigrants of whatever class, nation or creed, and procure for them situations free of charge." (1852 Oct 24)
William A. Graham (1804-1875), Secretary of the Navy, concerning the applications of various persons for assistance or for government positions such as the Virginian Mr. Chapman for purser in the Navy, a term of shore duty for Purser Forrest of the U.S.S. Ohio, David Taylor of North Carolina prosecuting a claim in the Indian Bureau, the application of William E. Hopkins for a commission upon the frigate Cumberland, the appointment of Tobias Wolfe as Naval Storekeeper at Memphis, the application of Commander John Rudd for a command in the Mediterranean Squadron, and inquires about the circumstances surrounding the death of James H. Norwood, Indian Agent, who was killed at Sergeants Bluff on the Missouri River (1850-1852)
Horace Greeley (1811-1872) discusses the advantages of his new Whig Almanac which he sends to Alexander H. H. Stuart, "I have endeavored in this Almanac to condense into a single view the essential characteristics of the two great antagonist parties which now so evenly divide the country. I think this view, if generally circulated, will exert a salutary influence on the formation of political sentiment in our country and that this may be felt, even in the approaching Presidential contest." (1852 Jan 25)
F. Gremger asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to visit the State Agricultural Fair of New York (1851 Sep 3)
William Grever asks Stuart to loan him enough money to pay off James J. Trotter in return for a deed of trust upon all his property (1850 Oct 3)
Benjamin Edwards Grey supplies a testimonial for John B. Temple and explains why he is willing to recommend Colonel Irwin to a clerkship (1852 Mar 17)
George G. Grove asking for his distributive share of the funds of the B. Buler estate (1851 Oct 12)
Francis Grund asks for copies of Alexander H. H. Stuart 's Report for The New York Herald and other newspapers (1851)
Hiland Hall (1795-1885) suggests that Judge Thornton's name should precede Mr. W[?]'s in the Secretary's instructions (1851 Sep 20)
Nathan Kelsey Hall (1810-1874) invites Alexander H. H. Stuart to Buffalo for a little reception for President Fillmore at the conclusion of his term and asks him to convince William A. Graham to attend as well (1853 Jan 5); and writes about Fillmore wondering if the remaining Fillmore Cabinet members would attend a reunion at Buffalo (1871 Jan 5)
J.K. Hanson encloses a letter from Hugh W. Sheffey referring to the bounty land warrant of his cousin Celly (1852 Apr 3)
J. Hardesty, President of the Rough and Ready Club of Rockingham County, which procured a silver pitcher to be presented to Alexander H. H. Stuart as a tribute (1848 Oct 25)
Kenton Harper writes enclosing the wills of Alex Grove and Lewis K Terrill and their effects from Camp Buena Vista following the Mexican War (1847 Dec 13); congratulates Alexander H. H. Stuart on his appointment as Secretary of the Interior (1850 Sep 14); mentions his service as commandant of the Port of Parras in the Mexican War (1850 Sep 30); discusses his appointment to the Chickasaw Indian Agency (1851 Mar 18); his report concerning affairs at the Chickasaw Agency and his concern that there are many white persons living in the Agency without regular permission (1851 Sep 15); concern over the run-down condition of the Agency farm and house, cost of hiring "a negro woman who belongs to an Indian," and the probability that he will only stay for one year (1851 Sep 15); encloses a copy of his letter to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, L. Lea, about purchasing farming implements for "the Caddos" and asks Alexander H. H. Stuart 's influence to have his son, George K. Harper, appointed agent for the purchase (1851 Sep 22); the complaints from the Chickasaws about the wild tribes trespassing upon their territory, a recent visit from the chief of the Caddos, George Washington, who said that his tribe had been driven out of Texas, and brought up to this country by his father, Chief Chonena, who asked for and received a strip of land on the Washita from the General Council of the Choctaws, producing a certificate signed by George Folsom, one of the Choctaw District Chiefs, to prove what he said. The Chief also said that General Armstrong had promised them farming implements and other tools so they could settle down on the land allotted to them by the Choctaws, in a group of about 300 to 400. An eleven year old Mexican girl rescued from Indian captivity was left in his care by his predecessor, Colonel Long and he asks what is to be done with her (1851 Sep 22); and his investigation of charges of a wagonload of liquor being brought into the Indian Territory for sale (1851 Oct 5).
J. Morrison Harris, Maryland Historical Society, informs Alexander H. H. Stuart of his honorary membership (1850 May 20)
Judge N. Harrison, Salt Sulphur Springs, Monroe County, West Virginia, writes concerning several suits in his court and business matters involving Alexander H. H. Stuart ([1869] Sep 3)
Solomon George Haven (1810-1861) hopes that Alexander H. H. Stuart will make a great impact in politics in the Old Dominion, and remarks about his own area, "I cannot tell you much of politics in this section [of New York ], there is almost a torpor. I have no choice between the democrats and the Republicans. The former is made up of the foreign votes here & the latter partly in the same way and partly of the very dishonest men amongst our native born citizens. The Americans have a most worthy state ticket in this State... Today the chances are in favor of the Republicans carrying the state but the battle has yet got to be set in array before results can be foretold. Perhaps the result of the struggle in Kansas and a full opening of Congress is necessary to give any form whatever, to the future" (1857 Oct 8).
A.M. Hay, his cousin, discusses the loss of her husband and the death of Alexander H. H. Stuart 's father, her plans to join her sister Mary in Athens, Greece, to help her run a boarding house for the upper class Greek girls attending the mission school, and requests Alexander H. H. Stuart 's aid in securing letters of introduction from Mr. Webster to the various consuls at ports of call along the way (1852 Aug 25)
T.S. Haymond explains the causes of the defeat of the Whig candidate for Governor of Virginia, George William Summers (1804-1868) in the recent election, in his area of Virginia, the northwestern section of the state [ Monongalia County, West Virginia ?] (1851 Dec 20)
Isaac Hazlehurst asks that Alexander H. H. Stuart send him copies of his articles signed "Madison" in reference to the American question (1857 Jun 24)
Richard H. Henderson, Virginia Colonization Society, refers to the "true policy of Virginia to keep down the free colored population of the state: that her legislature originated the scheme for colonizing this population beyond the borders of the United States; that appropriations have been well received by the people" and recommends extending the act to those slaves set free by wills; and "The prohibitions as to the admission of free blacks in the non- slaveholding states are well known; and, should the other southwestern states follow the example set them by Mississippi as they soon will, either a channel must be opened through which this population may flow off to Africa, or it will increase amongst us to a most mischievous extent." (1837 Oct 28)
Professor Joseph Henry, Smithsonian Institute, letter of introduction for Mr. F. [Bonynge] the author of a work on the culture of tea and indigo in the United States (1852 Aug 4)
Britton A. Hill writes enclosing his newspaper articles defending Alexander H. H. Stuart 's decision in the Labeaume land grant case which was attacked in The St. Louis Republican by the claimant Maguire (1852 Feb 6 & 9)
William L. Hodge encloses a newsclipping about the decision of Millard Fillmore not to be a candidate for the Presidency and how much such a declaration will injure Fillmore and the party (1852 Jan 20)
J.E. Holmes asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to recommend to the President that he increase the salary of District Judge Hoffman in San Francisco, California, lest he leave and an inferior officer replace him (1851 Oct 25)
Rev. Samuel Rutherford Houston to Dr. John J. Moorman seeking Alexander H. H. Stuart 's influence to have him appointed Principal of the Institution for the Deaf and Dumb in Staunton, Virginia (1852 Feb 24)
M.U. Houston both letters discuss the Wheeling Bridge case in which a suit was brought alleging that the Wheeling Bridge was not suitable for railroad purposes and Alexander H. H. Stuart 's role in the matter (1850 Mar 16 & Jun 8)
Benjamin Chew Howard refers to the Wheeling Bridge case and asks if Alexander H. H. Stuart wishes his brief to be inserted in his argument (1852 Jul 30)
Robert Hull acknowledges the receipt of a check which makes them even and encloses a graphic and highly complimentary sketch of Mr. Alexander H. H. Stuart from a Boston paper (1851 Oct 3)
Andrew Hunter writes about the "Beeler Case" and wishes to receive his administration fee now in Alexander H. H. Stuart 's hands (1851 Nov 27); and comments on his grief that Jefferson County has elected two Democrats to the Legislature, mentions other items about local Virginia politics, and the dissatisfaction of the voters at Harpers Ferry due to certain army regulations (1851 Nov 27 & Dec 9)
R.M.T. Hunter (1809-1887) asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to send an estimate of the expense of the wings of the Capitol to be included in the Civil and Diplomatic Bill (1852 Feb 3)
John Daniel Imboden (1823-1895) writes concerning the suit of Daniel Mosby against Thomas Johnson and Thomas Turk over possession of a tract of land and asks if Alexander H. H. Stuart has made any arrangements for someone to take over his legal cases (1850 Sep 23); his introduction of a series of land resolutions concerning the distribution of the proceeds from the sale of public lands approved by an act of Congress on September 4, 1841, and the possible use of such funds for the purpose of education, and asks Alexander H. H. Stuart to get a clerk to make a brief statement as to what appropriations of land have been made for educational and internal improvements, to what states, when, and for what specific objects, has hopes of carrying the Central Railroad this session along with other internal improvements, the great excitement over the next Presidential election with Millard Fillmore being the choice of the Virginia Whigs with Alexander H. H. Stuart being mentioned as the Vice-Presidential candidate (1852 Jan 31); writes again concerning the great Central line of improvement through Virginia, especially a proposition to construct a railroad from Covington to the Ohio River on state account and asks if he can negotiate the sale of stock in London or New York (1853 Jan 22)
Joseph K. Irving, San Francisco, writes through W.D. Fair, praising the fidelity of James M. Crane, editor of The California Courier, to Whig principles and doctrines, discusses "the gross frauds and outrageous wrongs inflicted and committed by the [Locofocos], in the matter of the contested seats" (1851 Mar 4); and introduces Dr. Wozencraft, California Indian agent (1852 Nov 30)
G.W. Israel asks for a donation for a seminary to train teachers of moderate circumstances to educate the lower classes (1853 Feb 8)
S.D. Jacobs refers to changes of mail routes proposed by R.G. Harmon (1851 Nov 13)
John Janney (1798-1872) writes concerning the necessity of resigning his position, as the Commissioner to West Virginia, due to his poor eyesight, unless the Legislature decides to settle the state debt question by agreeing to pay two-thirds of the debt and repudiating the balance, leaving the creditors of the state of Virginia to look to West Virginia for the residue (1866-1867)
G.N. Johnson concerning the legal case of the Bank of the United States vs Samuel Leake (1840 May 14)
R.[G.] Johnson writes about postponing the argument in a legal case, "the only question to be argued in the brief case, is, whether the act of Congress does not legalize the Brief" (1850-1853 all about this case)
William B. Kayser notifies Alexander H. H. Stuart that Dr. Hall has received payment through the Finley estate and has remitted five hundred dollars to Alexander H. H. Stuart drawn on the Bank of Winchester (1852 Sep 24)
John P. Kennedy (1795-1870) tries to secure a clerkship for a friend, Mr. Ridgate (1850 Sep 18); regards "every man now who places the Compromise [of 1850 ?] in the front of his creed a good and true Whig -and every convert to the Administration on that ground a new recruit to the standard of Whig principles" (1851 Apr 17); arrangements made for the ceremony connected with the committee on the Inauguration of the Statue (1853 Jan 7); attempts to persuade Alexander H. H. Stuart to accompany himself and Mr. Millard Fillmore on a trip south to Richmond, Charleston, Savannah, and then on to Cuba, West Indies, New Orleans and thence to Kentucky and home (1854 Feb 13)